[
    {
        "num": 6,
        "category": "Science",
        "subcategory": null,
        "difficulty": "MS",
        "tournament": "Collaborative MS Tournament",
        "question": "A pressure associated with this process is a colligative property proportional to mass and temperature, and is defined as the hydrostatic pressure necessary to counteract this process. A 'reverse' form of this process is sometimes used to purify water. Name this movement of water across a semi-permeable membrane from an area of high concentration to an area of low concentration.",
        "answers": ["osmosis", "diffusion"],
        "round": "CMST_Round06.pdf",
        "year": 2010
    },
    {
        "num": 17,
        "category": "Fine Arts",
        "subcategory": null,
        "difficulty": "MS",
        "tournament": "Collaborative MS Tournament",
        "question": "This artist's statues of a dying slave and a horned Moses were to adorn the tomb of Julius II. His only signed work is one in which Mary holds the dead body of Jesus, entitled Piet√†. One of his works depicts a nude giant killer holding a sling. This man depicted several scenes from Genesis in The Last Judgement. Name this Italian Renaissance painter of the Sistine Chapel ceiling.",
        "answers": ["Michelangelo", "Buonarroti"],
        "round": "CMST_Round05.pdf",
        "year": 2010
    },
    {
        "num": 3,
        "category": "Science",
        "subcategory": null,
        "difficulty": "MS",
        "tournament": "Collaborative MS Tournament",
        "question": "The size of these objects is given by the Schwarzschild radius. According to quantum mechanics, these objects emit Hawking radiation. One of them, Sagittarius A Star, sits at the center of our galaxy and has four million times the mass of our sun. Name these objects in outer space from which supposedly nothing, not even light, can escape?",
        "answers": ["black holes"],
        "round": "CMST_Round08.pdf",
        "year": 2010
    },
    {
        "num": 16,
        "category": "Literature",
        "subcategory": null,
        "difficulty": "MS",
        "tournament": "Collaborative MS Tournament",
        "question": "This character was named after the wife of King Leontes in The Winter's Tale. This character forms an organization called S.P.E.W., and purchases a half-cat, half-kneazle known as Crookshanks. Though she is called a 'mudblood' because of her dentist parents, she is smart enough to have memorized \"Hogwarts: A History.\" Name this female companion to Harry and Ron in the \"Harry Potter\" series.",
        "answers": ["Hermione Granger"],
        "round": "CMST_Round04.pdf",
        "year": 2010
    },
    {
        "num": 1,
        "category": "Fine Arts",
        "subcategory": null,
        "difficulty": "MS",
        "tournament": "Collaborative MS Tournament",
        "question": "Three square windows can be seen in the back of this painting, and the back of a chair takes up its lower center portion. The central figure is wearing red and blue with his hands on a table; to his right is an effeminate figure believed to be the Apostle John. Judas clutches a bag of silver in what Leonardo da Vinci painting that depicts Christ's final meal with his disciples?",
        "answers": ["The Last Supper"],
        "round": "CMST_Round01.pdf",
        "year": 2010
    },
    {
        "num": 2,
        "category": "Science",
        "subcategory": null,
        "difficulty": "MS",
        "tournament": "Collaborative MS Tournament",
        "question": "The 'law of' these objects states that the torque on one side is equal to the torque on the other side. These objects can be classified as first class, second class, or third class depending on the location of the fulcrum. Name these simple machines, familiar examples of which include a wheelbarrow and see-saw.",
        "answers": ["levers"],
        "round": "CMST_Round01.pdf",
        "year": 2010
    },
    {
        "num": 3,
        "category": "Geography",
        "subcategory": null,
        "difficulty": "MS",
        "tournament": "Collaborative MS Tournament",
        "question": "Landmarks on this island include the El Yunque rainforest and Fort San Felipe del Moro. Humacao, Caguas, Bayamon, and Ponce are some of its municipalities. The largest municipality shares the name given to the island by Columbus, San Juan. Identify this island, a United States commonwealth in the Caribbean.",
        "answers": ["Puerto Rico"],
        "round": "CMST_Round01.pdf",
        "year": 2010
    },
    {
        "num": 4,
        "category": "Literature",
        "subcategory": null,
        "difficulty": "MS",
        "tournament": "Collaborative MS Tournament",
        "question": "While travelling back to his hometown, this man solves a riddle with the answer of 'man.' He kills his own father over the right-of-way at a crossroads. This man fathers his daughter Antigone by his own mother Jocasta, fulfilling a prophecy made at his birth. Name this title character of plays by Sophocles, including one in which he is at Colonus and one in which he is Rex, or The King.",
        "answers": ["Oedipus"],
        "round": "CMST_Round01.pdf",
        "year": 2010
    },
    {
        "num": 5,
        "category": "History",
        "subcategory": null,
        "difficulty": "MS",
        "tournament": "Collaborative MS Tournament",
        "question": "Policies during this war included the \"strategic hamlet\" program and the use of Agent Orange as a defoliant. The Battle of Khe Sanh was fought during this war, which ended with the fall of Saigon, a city that was renamed after the victorious side's leader, Ho Chi Minh. A memorial wall in Washington, DC lists the American casualties of what conflict in Southeast Asia?",
        "answers": ["Vietnam War"],
        "round": "CMST_Round01.pdf",
        "year": 2010
    },
    {
        "num": 6,
        "category": "Science",
        "subcategory": null,
        "difficulty": "MS",
        "tournament": "Collaborative MS Tournament",
        "question": "The DNA in this organelle is inherited only from the mother. The inner membrane of this organelle contains folds known as cristae and encloses its matrix. This organelle is the site of oxidative phosphorylation, which occurs at the end of the electron transport chain. Name this organelle responsible for cellular respiration, which produces ATP and thus provides energy for the cell.",
        "answers": ["mitochondria", "mitochondrion"],
        "round": "CMST_Round01.pdf",
        "year": 2010
    },
    {
        "num": 7,
        "category": "Literature",
        "subcategory": null,
        "difficulty": "MS",
        "tournament": "Collaborative MS Tournament",
        "question": "The most winning woman he ever knew was hanged for poisoning three little children for their insurance-money. Irene Adler, always THE woman to this man, outwitted him during his investigation of 'A Scandal in Bohemia.' This man returned in 'The Adventure of the Empty House' after battling Professor Moriarty to the death. Name this detective faithfully accompanied by John Watson.",
        "answers": ["Sherlock Holmes"],
        "round": "CMST_Round01.pdf",
        "year": 2010
    },
    {
        "num": 8,
        "category": "Fine Arts",
        "subcategory": null,
        "difficulty": "MS",
        "tournament": "Collaborative MS Tournament",
        "question": "This man composed a ballet called The Creatures of Prometheus, and Leonato is a major character in his opera Fidelio. His third symphony was originally written to honor Napoleon and was called Eroica. A later symphony by this man borrows from Schiller's \"Ode to Joy\" for its choral final movement. Name this composer whose fifth symphony begins with a fate knocking at the door theme and who went deaf.",
        "answers": ["Ludwig von Beethoven", "beethoven"],
        "round": "CMST_Round01.pdf",
        "year": 2010
    },
    {
        "num": 9,
        "category": "History",
        "subcategory": null,
        "difficulty": "MS",
        "tournament": "Collaborative MS Tournament",
        "question": "The oldest person to hold this position was Roger Taney. This office serves as Chancellor of the Smithsonian, and also presides over Presidential impeachment trials. It was held by Charles Evans Hughes, John Marshall, and Earl Warren, the latter of whom wrote an opinion that mandated the so-called 'Miranda Rights'. Name this position currently held by John Roberts Jr., the head of the federal judiciary.",
        "answers": ["Chief Justice of the Supreme Court", "chief justice"],
        "round": "CMST_Round01.pdf",
        "year": 2010
    },
    {
        "num": 10,
        "category": "Science",
        "subcategory": null,
        "difficulty": "MS",
        "tournament": "Collaborative MS Tournament",
        "question": "The Euler line passes through the orthocenter, circumcenter, and centroid in this figure. The area of this polygon can be found by halving the product of two sides and the sine of the angle opposite of the third side or by simply using Heron's formula. It is the only polygon that cannot be concave, because its angles must add to 180 degrees. Name this polygon with three sides.",
        "answers": ["triangle"],
        "round": "CMST"
    },
    {
        "num": 11,
        "category": "History",
        "subcategory": null,
        "difficulty": "MS",
        "tournament": "Collaborative MS Tournament",
        "question": "In the buildup to this battle, the losing commander set up a fortification at Gloucester shortly after retreating from Williamsburg. A key turning point in this battle was the arrival of reinforcements under Count Rochambeau. British naval forces under Thomas Graves failed to break through the French blockade. Name this final Revolutionary War battle, after which Lord Cornwallis surrendered.",
        "answers": ["Battle of Yorktown"],
        "round": "CMST_Round01.pdf",
        "year": 2010
    },
    {
        "num": 12,
        "category": "Trash",
        "subcategory": null,
        "difficulty": "MS",
        "tournament": "Collaborative MS Tournament",
        "question": "He compared himself to Robert Downey Jr. on a Colbert Report appearance in which he defended himself from rumors of a lifestyle change. While Kermit the Frog lectured about the W, this character turned it into an N, a V, and then an I. He notes, \"that's good enough for me\" while singing about what C is for. Name this blue Muppet known for catchphrases like \"Me want cookie!\".",
        "answers": ["Cookie Monster"],
        "round": "CMST_Round01.pdf",
        "year": 2010
    },
    {
        "num": 13,
        "category": "Science",
        "subcategory": null,
        "difficulty": "MS",
        "tournament": "Collaborative MS Tournament",
        "question": "One theory of this entity's creation states that a Mars-sized body named Theia collided with its parent planet. This object exhibits synchronous rotation with its parent planet, and that rotation results in the namesake \"dark side\" of this object. The Sea of Tranquility lies on what astronomical body responsible for the Earth's tides, its largest natural satellite?",
        "answers": ["Moon"],
        "round": "CMST_Round01.pdf",
        "year": 2010
    },
    {
        "num": 14,
        "category": "Literature",
        "subcategory": null,
        "difficulty": "MS",
        "tournament": "Collaborative MS Tournament",
        "question": "This man wrote about an animal who steals from the farmers Boggis, Bunce and Bean in The Fantastic Mister Fox. He also wrote about a girl with psychic powers who reads every book in the library and then loses her powers in Miss Honey's class in his book Matilda. A better known book by this man sees its title fruit get stuck on top of the Empire State Building. Name this author of James and the Giant Peach.",
        "answers": ["Roald Dahl", "Dahl"],
        "round": "CMST_Round01.pdf",
        "year": 2010
    },
    {
        "num": 16,
        "category": "Religion",
        "subcategory": null,
        "difficulty": "MS",
        "tournament": "Collaborative MS Tournament",
        "question": "One variety of this faith is outlined in the Pali Canon. Another variety venerates those who become enlightened but remain in samsara, called bodhisattvas. Those varieties are Theravada and Mahayana.  Adherents to another variety of this faith meditate on koans such as \"What is the sound of one hand clapping?\". Name this Asian faith that venerates Siddhartha Gautama.",
        "answers": ["Buddhism"],
        "round": "CMST_Round01.pdf",
        "year": 2010
    },
    {
        "num": 17,
        "category": "Mythology",
        "subcategory": null,
        "difficulty": "MS",
        "tournament": "Collaborative MS Tournament",
        "question": "He fulfilled a prophecy by accidentally killing his grandfather Acrisius with a discus. Acrisius had imprisoned his mother, Danae, but Zeus visited her as a golden shower. This man borrowed the invisibility cap of Hades, the reflective shield of Athena, and the winged sandals of Hermes. He slew a sea monster that was about to consume Andromeda, whom he made his wife. Name this figure who beheaded Medusa.",
        "answers": ["Perseus"],
        "round": "CMST_Round01.pdf",
        "year": 2010
    },
    {
        "num": 18,
        "category": "Science",
        "subcategory": null,
        "difficulty": "MS",
        "tournament": "Collaborative MS Tournament",
        "question": "The Andean type of these entities occurs beneath a continental plate, and it is at these sites that about 20% of Earth's crust has been consumed. This antithesis of the mid-oceanic ridge is usually typified by lines of volcanoes running parallel near an oceanic trench. Identify this region where tectonic plates collide, and one goes underneath the other.",
        "answers": ["subduction zone"],
        "round": "CMST_Round01.pdf",
        "year": 2010
    },
    {
        "num": 19,
        "category": "Literature",
        "subcategory": null,
        "difficulty": "MS",
        "tournament": "Collaborative MS Tournament",
        "question": "This man described a trip around America with his poodle in Travels with Charley. In a novella by this man, George shoots Lennie to prevent him from being lynched. This man also wrote about the Joad family's attempt to escape the Depression by moving to California from Oklahoma. Identify this American author of Of Mice and Men and The Grapes of Wrath.",
        "answers": ["John Ernst Steinbeck"],
        "round": "CMST_Round01.pdf",
        "year": 2010
    },
    {
        "num": 20,
        "category": "History",
        "subcategory": null,
        "difficulty": "MS",
        "tournament": "Collaborative MS Tournament",
        "question": "This man fought against Ariovistus, a German leader, and Vercingetorix, a chieftain of the Arverni whose defeat is described in this man's book, Commentaries on the Gallic Wars. He led his troops across the Rubicon to start a civil war with Pompey, one of his partners in the First Triumvirate. Name this Roman leader who was assassinated by Brutus on the Ides of March.",
        "answers": ["Julius Caesar"],
        "round": "CMST_Round01.pdf",
        "year": 2010
    },
    {
        "num": 1,
        "category": "Science",
        "subcategory": null,
        "difficulty": "MS",
        "tournament": "Collaborative MS Tournament",
        "question": "One piece of evidence that supports its existence is that the Caledonian mountains of Northern Europe are a continuation of the Appalachian Mountains. This entity broke up into Laurasia and Gondwanaland. Alfred Wegener coined its name during a lecture in which he discussed his theory of continental drift. Name this supercontinent theorized to have existed 250 million years ago.",
        "answers": ["Pangaea"],
        "round": "CMST_Round02.pdf",
        "year": 2010
    },
    {
        "num": 2,
        "category": "History",
        "subcategory": null,
        "difficulty": "MS",
        "tournament": "Collaborative MS Tournament",
        "question": "This person declared we are \"one people\" during a run against Alan Keyes. A later campaign opponent of this person used Joe the Plumber to attack this person's policies and attempted to link this person to Bill Ayers. This person used the slogan \"Yes We Can\" and won the Nobel Peace Prize after less than a year in office. Who is this successor of George W. Bush and current President of the United States?",
        "answers": ["Barack Hussein Obama II"],
        "round": "CMST_Round02.pdf",
        "year": 2010
    },
    {
        "num": 3,
        "category": "Geography",
        "subcategory": null,
        "difficulty": "MS",
        "tournament": "Collaborative MS Tournament",
        "question": "The island of Bornholm is in this body of water, which is connected by the Kiel Canal to the North Sea. One arm of this sea is the Gulf of Bothnia, and the large island of Saaremaa guards its Gulf of Riga. Five national capitals lie on this body of water, including Tallinn, the capital of Estonia, and Stockholm. Name this sea south of Scandinavia.",
        "answers": ["Baltic Sea"],
        "round": "CMST_Round02.pdf",
        "year": 2010
    },
    {
        "num": 4,
        "category": "Literature",
        "subcategory": null,
        "difficulty": "MS",
        "tournament": "Collaborative MS Tournament",
        "question": "In this novel, a town is fooled by two men who pull off the Royal Nonesuch, and those men go on to steal the property of the late Peter Wilkes. The Widow Douglas wants to \"sivilize\" the title character, who misses a turn at Cairo and keeps floating south. Name this novel that sees Jim and the title friend of Tom Sawyer travel down the Mississippi River, a work by Mark Twain.",
        "answers": ["The Adventures of Huckleberry Finn"],
        "round": "CMST_Round02.pdf",
        "year": 2010
    },
    {
        "num": 5,
        "category": "History",
        "subcategory": null,
        "difficulty": "MS",
        "tournament": "Collaborative MS Tournament",
        "question": "This party was founded by several ex-Whigs. Past leaders of this party include Newt Gingrich, the creator of the Contract with America, and Teddy Roosevelt. One member of this party made a campaign pledge of \"no new taxes,\" and Libertarians traditionally run under this major party's banner. It is currently chaired by Michael Steele. Name this major party also called the \"Grand Old Party.\"",
        "answers": ["Republican Party"],
        "round": "CMST_Round02.pdf",
        "year": 2010
    },
    {
        "num": 6,
        "category": "Science",
        "subcategory": null,
        "difficulty": "MS",
        "tournament": "Collaborative MS Tournament",
        "question": "Two liquids are said to be immiscible if they cannot combine to form this type of mixture. In the most common form of this mixture, solid particles are small enough to completely dissolve in a liquid. Name this type of mixture that is not a colloid or suspension, an example of which is sugar dissolved in water.",
        "answers": ["solution"],
        "round": "CMST_Round02.pdf",
        "year": 2010
    },
    {
        "num": 7,
        "category": "Trash",
        "subcategory": null,
        "difficulty": "MS",
        "tournament": "Collaborative MS Tournament",
        "question": "At one point in this musical, Dr. Dillamond sings \"Something Bad.\" At another point, Madame Morrible announces that the main character is now an enemy of the town, and that character then sings \"Defying Gravity.\" The two heroines in it were originally played by Kristin Chenoweth and Idina Menzel. The relationship between Elphaba and Glinda is documented in what musical based on The Wizard of Oz?",
        "answers": ["Wicked"],
        "round": "CMST_Round02.pdf",
        "year": 2010
    },
    {
        "num": 8,
        "category": "Literature",
        "subcategory": null,
        "difficulty": "MS",
        "tournament": "Collaborative MS Tournament",
        "question": "One of this writer's stories follows Annemarie Johansen as she helps her friend Ellen escape from Nazi-occupied Denmark. A sequel to this author's most well-known book follows the weaver Kira, and that book ends with Jonah and Gabe fleeing the dystopian society they live in. Identify this Newbery award winning author who wrote Number the Stars, Gathering Blue, and The Giver.",
        "answers": ["Lois Lowry"],
        "round": "CMST_Round02.pdf",
        "year": 2010
    },
    {
        "num": 9,
        "category": "History",
        "subcategory": null,
        "difficulty": "MS",
        "tournament": "Collaborative MS Tournament",
        "question": "This man's wife Jiang Qing was a member of the Gang of Four. He escaped a Kuomintang offensive led by Chiang Kai-shek and went on the Long March in 1934. After he took power in 1949, his government adopted such policies as the Great Leap Forward and the Cultural Revolution. The Little Red Book was written by what Chairman of China's Communist Party?",
        "answers": ["Mao Zedong"],
        "round": "CMST_Round02.pdf",
        "year": 2010
    },
    {
        "num": 10,
        "category": "Religion",
        "subcategory": null,
        "difficulty": "MS",
        "tournament": "Collaborative MS Tournament",
        "question": "During his execution, this figure was pierced by the Lance of Longinus. In addition to yelling at a fig tree for not bearing fruit, this figure healed a pig-eating man from Gerasa possessed by a horde of devils named Legion. This man was put to death by Pontius Pilate, and drops of his blood fell into the Holy Grail. Name this Messiah and only son of God according to Christianity.",
        "answers": ["Jesus Christ"],
        "round": "CMST_Round02.pdf",
        "year": 2010
    },
    {
        "num": 11,
        "category": "Science",
        "subcategory": null,
        "difficulty": "MS",
        "tournament": "Collaborative MS Tournament",
        "question": "This constellation is often interpreted as fighting Taurus with his dogs Canis Minor and Canis Major. Stars within this constellation include the \"amazon star\" Bellatrix, the red giant Betelgeuse (\"beetle juice\"), and Rigel. It is most easily recognizable by the three stars making up the belt of the figure in this constellation. Name this constellation also known as \"the Hunter.\"",
        "answers": ["Orion"],
        "round": "CMST_Round02.pdf",
        "year": 2010
    },
    {
        "num": 12,
        "category": "Literature",
        "subcategory": null,
        "difficulty": "MS",
        "tournament": "Collaborative MS Tournament",
        "question": "This play's opening brawl is started by Gregory and Samson. Later in this play, Friar John fails to deliver a letter written by Friar Lawrence. Mercutio is killed by Tybalt in Act III of this play. This play features the feud between the Montagues and the Capulets. Name this Shakespeare tragedy, depicting a doomed romance between the two title \"star-crossed lovers.\"",
        "answers": ["Romeo and Juliet"],
        "round": "CMST_Round02.pdf",
        "year": 2010
    },
    {
        "num": 13,
        "category": "History",
        "subcategory": null,
        "difficulty": "MS",
        "tournament": "Collaborative MS Tournament",
        "question": "After having much of his legislation overturned by the Supreme Court, this leader proposed his court packing plan. The Tennessee Valley Authority was one piece of New Deal legislation that was not overturned by the Court. Although he led his country for most of World War II, he did not make the decision to drop the atomic bombs on Japan. He succeeded Herbert Hoover. Who is the only President of the United States to be elected to more than two terms in office?",
        "answers": ["Franklin Delano Roosevelt"],
        "round": "CMST_Round02.pdf",
        "year": 2010
    },
    {
        "num": 14,
        "category": "Fine Arts",
        "subcategory": null,
        "difficulty": "MS",
        "tournament": "Collaborative MS Tournament",
        "question": "On the right side of this painting, a large gray rectangle is cut off by the edge of the canvas. In the back of the painting, a body of water is seen; to the right of that water, the Cliffs of Cadaques are yellow. Its center depicts a white \"monster,\" and another object in this painting is upside down and covered in ants. Name this painting that features melting clocks, a work by Salvador Dali.",
        "answers": ["The Persistence of Memory"],
        "round": "CMST_Round02.pdf",
        "year": 2010
    },
    {
        "num": 15,
        "category": "Science",
        "subcategory": null,
        "difficulty": "MS",
        "tournament": "Collaborative MS Tournament",
        "question": "The harmonic one of n numbers in a data set is n divided by the sum of the reciprocals of the numbers. The geometric one is the nth root of the product of the numbers. The geometric one is always less than or equal to the arithmetic one. What is this term in mathematics\u2014the arithmetic one being the sum of the numbers divided by n?",
        "answers": ["mean"],
        "round": "CMST_Round02.pdf",
        "year": 2010
    }
]
